This task is about the modification of a program.
Again we have been given a
result as it shall look like,
which we can view in CodeWorld and I load it now.
There we see, we shall draw a
circle which is growing bigger, then
reducing its size, and finally
fitting at the final state.
Actually how big the circle gets and at what
rate it is increasing is up to the programmer.
We have been given this program here.
If we run this, we see that there
is a circle which is growing,
and growing, and growing, and growing,
and growing, and growing. It never stops.
Now we shall modify the program.
The 'balloon' function is the
function that we want to modify,
because this draws the solid
circle that we get in the end.
We want to
modify this in a way that we have certain time
steps and certain sizes at specific times.
The size of the circle is
defined by this function here.
So in this case we multiply
0.5 by t and if we want to increase the
speed, we just increase the factor before t.
So we want to have a smooth motion of the balloon
when it's increasing and then
it's going to the next stage.
It shall stay the same size and not suddenly jump
to it or to different sizes - so that's
something we have to consider as well.
So we could stop moving the
circle at a certain point.
I use guards here in order to achieve this.
So I define a certain time
point - which is time1 - and
I say this is just some turn
point let's say - two seconds.
And we can increase the solid circle
until this time point is reached and then
we can stop the animation - which is not what
we want to achieve in this particular case.
Or let's just keep these values, so
we could say, we have 0.5 and then
in this case, if we apply this
nothing changes or nothing happens,
but if we say - we have reached
time1, we want to keep the size.
We just apply time1 and then our animation
would finally stop at this point and the
balloon is not growing anymore.
We can have a second stage however
where the balloon shall shrink.
So now we have to figure out a second
time point let's say it's time2.
This one defines also a solid circle
but with different parameters.
We can think about this in a moment.
This is time point2. And this one
shall be bigger than the first one.
And we do not check within the guard if - so we
could check that t is greater than or equal to time1,
but as we have learned in the lecture
this is actually not required to do.
And actually it's also bad style -
we should leave this out - because
if the first guard does not apply the second
will, and so we can just skip this step
because we know time1 doesn't
apply anymore so time2 shall apply.
We've seen in the animation now that
the time2 point is not the exact
point for stopping the animation.
So we could just say here time2 shall be the
point where it all stops and then we could
move to this point and
then it will stop properly.
I want to define the size of the balloon as well.
So I want to have the sizes at the
stages when it ends - so the first one is
size1 and let's say this is six and
the last one is size2 and this is two
and time point2 change it to three so just to
increase the speed of the animation so that
it finishes a bit earlier and now when I want
to reach size1 at a certain point of time.
And I want to reach size1 when time1 is reached.
I could simply say size1
is reached exactly when I
divide size1 by time1 and multiply by
t, because if we reach time1 then t and
time1 are equal and thus I just divide by time1
and multiply by time1 and then I reach size1.
So running this will finish the first
stage with a balloon of size six
and now we have this jump which
we have to get rid of, of course.
Now we have to figure out what
happens in the second stage.
I say I want to get to
size2 after reaching time2.
First of all, when we start this stage
the time point is time1 here t is
greater than or it's equal to
time1 but it's less than time2.
We have the size1 which is the starting point
and now we subtract something - we subtract
the difference between the sizes at
these particular time steps. Right?
We have size2 minus size1 - oh well -
A different way of saying
this: we add the difference,
right? When we get from size1 to size2.
We add the difference which is in this case
minus 4 or let's say size2 minus size1,
which is: 2 minus 6 is -4 and now we
do again the same trick as before.
We have to think of the time moments
again because when we reach the first
time point then we have a certain amount
of time - which is the difference between
time2 and time1 - that's the amount
that our balloon shall be shrinking.
We divide by this time - this is the difference,
right, so time2 minus time1. That's the time we want
to decrease the size of the border by, that's
time2 minus time1 - so in fact 1 second.
Then we multiply by t - well t
is not correct because when we
reach time point one then we want to
have just the size at this time point.
So it or all the later time
points, which is t minus time1.
We can say t minus time1 and this is
what we multiply it by in order to
achieve the size we have in the last stage.
The size of the last stage is just
- the size of - it's just size 2.
That's what we want to reach in the final stage.
If we apply this, then we see we get an
increasing balloon and a shrinking one
and we end at the exact size of size 2. Okay?
I want to just stress one point,
your solution should not contain something like
this here: t is greater than or equal to time2
because this would lead to a non-exhaustiveness
or could lead to a non-exhaustiveness warning.
And as that may not be able to
figure out what's happening here,
that's why we use the otherwise here. Okay?
And now there is just a little detail
missing and that's the coloring.
For all these circles there
shall be coloring additionally
and I want to have different colors here.
We can choose any color.
There is no color given; we have to choose.
So we can just say colored
green for the first one, and
colored yellow for the second one,
and colored red for the third one.
It's now like the traffic lights
- when it stops it's red.
We can also extract a function here.
In order to draw the circle.
We would like that, so we can use - say
colored circle is with color and size is
colored, spell it like this: color
colored color - and then solid
circle with the given size
and then we can refactor the
code by using the coloredCircle.
Say here: coloredCircle green and then we can
reuse this part in all of our parts in order to
reduce the size of the code a bit.
coloredCircle and then
So size two, this is the same code
- actually just a bit refactored
now we have all our circles colored by
giving a parameter for color and the size.
Then we - maybe to decrease the line
size - we can write the code like this.
Then it fits better on this screen
and now if we want to change the animation we
simply can change the time spaces for instance:
time1 one, time2 two - and this will be
a faster animation - still does the same.
But be aware you shall not change time2
below time1 or equal; if you do this then
one step is missing, because then the second
step is skipped because this one covers
the second step as well -
so this should not happen.
And also if you change the first value to
zero or below, this step will also be skipped
and if you run the code now you
will see there is just the red ball.
So keep in mind that you shall have
positive values for these circles and
if you didn't have it for your submission
you will not get points for your submission.
But if the animation is smooth,
thus it does not jump and
all the three animation phases
are visible, then you're fine.